<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- vim: set ts=2 expandtab: -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5988 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5988.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3694 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3694.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5870 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5870.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6280 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6280.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6690 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6690.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
<?rfc inline="yes" ?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-fossati-core-geo-link-format-attribute-03" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="The geo Link-Format Attribute">
      A Link-Format Attribute for Locating Things
    </title>
    <author fullname="Thomas Fossati" initials="T.F." surname="Fossati">
      <organization>Alcatel-Lucent</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>3 Ely Road</street>
          <city>Milton, Cambridge</city>
          <code>CB24 6DD</code>
          <country>UK</country>
        </postal>
        <email>thomas.fossati@alcatel-lucent.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2014" month="February" />

    <area>General</area>
    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <keyword>CoAP, Link Format, geo link-format attribute, geo tagging sensors</keyword>

    <abstract>
	    <t>This memo proposes a new CoAP link format attribute, "geo", that can be used to associate positioning metadata to a CoAP resource.  An extension to the link format query syntax is also defined to allow the discovery of resources based on their geo location.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The ability for a client application to access positioning information about a sensing resource is crucial in a number of use cases, e.g. those in which one or more sensor networks provide input to an emergency handling service (fire, flood, etc.).</t>
      <t>This memo proposes a new CoAP link-format attribute, "geo", that can be used to associate positioning metadata to a CoAP resource, and make this information available to other endpoints that, directly or indirectly, participate to CoAP link-format discovery <xref target="RFC6690" />.</t>
      <t>This spec reuses the geo URI syntax <xref target="RFC5870"/>, which is capable of describing physical locations in two or three dimensions (also supporting underground and underwater localisation using negative numbers) in a simple, reasonably compact, and human readable way.</t>

      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119" />.</t>
      </section>  <!-- Requirement Language -->

    </section>  <!-- Introduction -->

    <section title="Use Cases">
      <t>Location-aware applications and location-based services like rescue systems in devastated areas, seismic networks, gas pipeline monitoring deployments, fire or flood detection systems, etc., need to precisely locate the source of sensed stimulus in order to react in a suitable way.  Smart city scenarios, e.g. street lights control, emergency services, often have similar needs.</t>
    </section>  <!-- Use Cases -->

    <section title="The geo Link Format Attribute">
      <t>This section defines a new Web Linking <xref target="RFC5988" /> link-param, "geo", to be used within the <xref target="RFC6690"/> framework, having the following syntax:</t>
      <figure>
        <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
        link-extension  = "geo" "=" geo-path
        geo-path          ; defined in Section 3.3. of RFC 5870
        ]]></artwork>
     </figure>
      <t>The geo attribute MUST NOT appear more than once in a link.</t>
      <!--
      <t>(NOTE about Link-Format queries: non exact matches cannot be easily/effectively queried.  To allow effective location-based queries, we should either extend the query filtering rules defined in Section 4.1 of <xref target="RFC6690" />, or split the geo attribute into its explicit axes.)</t>
    -->
    </section>  <!-- The geo Link Format Attribute -->

    <section title="Examples" anchor="examples">
      <t><list style="symbols"><t>A sensor exposing an explicit location resource:</t></list></t>
      <figure>
        <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
  REQ: GET /.well-known/core?geo=*

  RES: 2.05 Content
  </loc>;geo="52.2047, 0.1368"
        ]]></artwork>
     </figure>

      <t><list style="symbols"><t>A fire detector somewhere in the Pollino National Park (approx. 10cm accuracy, enough to distinguish trees from each other):</t></list></t>
      <figure>
        <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
  REQ: GET /.well-known/core?geo=*

  RES: 2.05 Content
  </fire>;ct=0;if="sensor";geo="40.00201,16.34007"
        ]]></artwork>
     </figure>
     <t><list style="symbols"><t>An underwater current sampler in the sea between Ithaki and Kefallonia bearing explicit accuracy information (10m):</t></list></t>
     <figure>
        <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
  REQ: GET /.well-known/core?geo=*

  RES: 2.05 Content
  </water>;ct=0;if="sensor";geo="38.2953,20.6426,-20;u=10"
        ]]></artwork>
      </figure>
    </section>  <!-- Examples -->

    <section title="Encoding Considerations">
      <t>This specification allows only one CRS, which is WGS-84.  There is no need to set an explicit crslabel when encoding a geo link-format attribute, since the default value wgs84 applies anyway.</t>
      <!--
      <t>It is RECOMMENDED to avoid setting an explicit crslabel if the default WGS-84 CRS is used.</t>
      -->
      <t>For further encoding consideration, see Section 3.5. of <xref target="RFC5870" />.</t>
    </section>  <!-- Encoding Considerations -->

    <section title="Extended Geo Queries" anchor="geo-query">

      <t>The "extended" geo query (xgeo) format allows a client application to select a capture area, and let endpoints advertise their presence -- by replying to the link-format query -- if they are located within the specified area.</t>

      <section title="Syntax"> 
        <t>The syntax for describing the query capture area is based on the "WGS 84 bounding box" defined in section 10.2.2 of <xref target="OGC-WSC" />.</t>
        <t>The WGS 84 bounding box is a specialisation of the more general bounding box concept for use with the WGS 84 geodetic datum, with latitude and longitude expressed as decimal degrees.</t>
        <t>A bounding box is a rectangular area identified by its lower and upper corners, i.e. the points within the bounding box at which the value of each coordinate is the algebraic minimum and maximum, respectively.</t>
        <t>For consistency with the geo URI definition, the latitude and longitude attributes of the upper and lower corners have been swapped, while the optional 'crs' and 'dimensions' parameters are not used (their default values are implicitly assumed), which leads to the following ABNF:
        <figure>
          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
        ext-geo-query = "?xgeo=" bounding-box
        bounding-box  = lower-corner "-" upper-corner
        lower-corner  = latitude "," longitude
        upper-corner  = latitude "," longitude
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        </t>
        <t>For simplicity, xgeo allows a single bounding box per link-format query.  Therefore, when a search is logically made of multiple boxes (e.g. at a discontinuity point, or for more complex tessellations), the querying client shall split it into the appropriate number of xgeo queries and send them out individually.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Filtering Rules">
        <t>An endpoint which understands xgeo MUST respond to the query if and only if its latitude and longitude values fall within the bounding box specified in the query string.</t>
        <t>When running the match algorithm, the queried endpoint MUST take into consideration any accuracy/uncertainty associated with its current position.  Any uncertainty information MUST be returned in a response if it has been used to compute a positive answer to the corresponding xgeo query.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Examples">
        <t><list style="symbols"><t>An example capture area that would match (among the other) the "/water" resource in <xref target="examples" />:</t></list></t>
        <t>
        <figure>
          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
  REQ: GET /.well-known/core?xgeo=38.2900,20.6400-38.3000,20.6500

  RES[0]: 2.05 Content
  </water>;geo="38.2953,20.6426,-20;u=10"

  RES[1]: 2.05 Content
  </pos>;geo="38.2908,20.6451"

  RES[2]: [...]

          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>  <!-- Geo Queries -->

    <?rfc needLines="8" ?>
    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Thanks to
        Keith Drage and
        Carl Reed
        for comments and discussions that have helped shaping this document.
      </t>
    </section>


    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>No formal request at present.  However, there is a plan to add a registry for the namespace of link parameters as part of <xref target="RFC5988" /> update.</t>
    <!--
      <t>Really needed?</t>
      <t><list style="symbols">
        <t>Attribute Value: geo</t> 
        <t>Description: associate positioning metadata to the linked resource.</t> 
        <t>Reference: this memo</t> 
      </list></t>
    -->
    </section>  <!-- IANA Considerations -->

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The "geo" link-format attribute shares the same security issues as any other attribute involved in the discovery process described in <xref target="RFC6690" />.</t>
      <t>Further to that, the privacy considerations regarding distribution, protection, usage, retention, and storage of the location information of the target resource found in <xref target="RFC6280" /> fully apply.</t>
    </section>  <!-- Security Considerations -->

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC2119;
      &RFC3694;
      &RFC5870;
      &RFC5988;
      &RFC6280;
      &RFC6690;
      <reference anchor="OGC-WSC" target="http://http://www.opengeospatial.org/standards/common">
        <front>
          <title>OGC Web Service Common Implementation Specification (Version 2.0.0)</title>
          <author initials="A." surname="Whiteside"></author>
          <author initials="J." surname="Greenwood"></author>
          <date year="2010" month="April" />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
